Guide to the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Lives Manuscript Collection, 1990-2002
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Lives Manuscript Collection
1990-2002
Vassar College. Library
1.4 cubic feet (3 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Memoirs, manuscripts, diaries, correspondence and other materials documenting the lives of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender persons affiliated with Vassar College.
Administrative History
Planning for the Vassar College Libraries' Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Lives Collection began in 1996 when Psychology professor John Schoonbeck approached Vassar College librarian Nancy Mackechnie about creating a collection of primary-source records documenting the experiences of LGBT members of the Vassar College community. The initial mission of the project was to provide research materials that were by and about lesbians and gay men affiliated with Vassar College. As the project evolved, it grew to include bisexual and transgender members of the community, although the final title of the project was officially "The Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Lives Library Project." Inclusion of "Transgender" into the project title was considered in March 2000 at the suggestion of Shannon Wyss (VC 1995), but ultimately rejected by the project oversight committee, although the project description was amended to include a mention of transgender experiences.
Scope and Content Note
Memoirs, manuscripts, diaries, correspondence and other materials documenting the lives of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender persons affiliated with Vassar College. Unpublished material was solicited in 1999 and received between 1999 and 2001. In addition, some early funding was used to purchase books and videos relating to LGBT life for the Main Library.
Access
The Baguer manuscript and Wyss correspondence are currently restricted. This rest of the collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
David McDaniel and Richard Redlon Papers, 1980-1990
LAGA-VC (Lesbians and Gay Alumnae/i - Vassar College) Records
Vassar College LGBTQ Oral History Project
Other writings by Anne MacKay housed in the Vassar College Alumnae/i Collection can be found by searching the Vassar College Online Catalog. These include MacKay's published books, collections of poetry, five unpublished works of Lesbian Science Fiction written in the 1990s, and the oral history of MacKay's transgender friend, Sandy Dee, which MacKay transcribed and edited.
Subject Headings
Names:
Anderson, Tobias; Baguer, Carlos; Lieber, Jeffrey (Jeffrey D.); MacKay, Anne, 1928-2012; Wyss, Shannon
Organizations:
Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae
Subjects:
Lesbians' writings; Gay men's writings; Gay college students--New York (State); Lesbian college students--New York (State); Transgender college students--New York (State); Bisexual college students--New York (State)
Document Types:
Correspondence; Diaries; Drafts
VCL Categories:
LGBTQ (Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual,Transgender & Queer) Life and Culture; Literature and Writing; Vassar College
Note
Forms part of the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Lives Collection.
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, January 2009. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, July 2025.
Acquisition Information
The journals of Tobias Anderson were the gift of Tobias Anderson, August 1999.
The Shannon Wyss letters and paper were the gift of Shannon Wyss, January 2000.
The thesis of Carlos Baguer was the gift of Carlos Baguer, March 2000.
The class paper written by Jeffrey D. Lieber was the gift of Jeffrey D. Lieber, April 2000.
Anne MacKay's drafts of "Just Lucky, I guess!" and poem collections from 1999 and 2000 were the gift of Anne Mackay, February 2001. Materials related to MacKay's book, "Wolf Girls at Vassar," were gifted by MacKay in 2002 and incorporated into the LGBT Lives Collection in 2009. [M2002-008]
Series List
- Series I. Tobias Anderson (VC 1998), 1992-2002; (12 volumes)
  Twelve volumes, including diaries, dream journals, and some class notes.
  Arranged chronologically.
- Series II. Carlos Baguer (VC 1996), (1 folder)
  Baguer's Vassar senior thesis, "No Se Dice Nada, Se Haga Todo": The Not-So-Secret History of My Familial Closet.
  Note: Due to third-party privacy issues, this collection is currently restricted.
- Series III. Jeffrey Lieber (VC 1997), 1993; (1 folder)
  A paper Lieber wrote for a Vassar English class in his first year of college.
- Series IV. Anne MacKay (VC 1949), 1990-2002; (2 boxes)
  Primarily materials related to her book, Wolf Girls at Vassar: Lesbian and Gay Experiences, 1930-1990, an unpublished manuscript of memoirs entitled, Just Lucky, I Guess!: Memoirs of a Wolf Girl or Growing up in Sheep's Clothing, drafts of poetry, an audio cassette of Vassar speeches given by MacKay(?), and miscellaneous other writings.
  Arranged into two subseries and sub-arranged alphabetically by title.
- Series V. Shannon Wyss (VC 1995), 1991-2000; (2 folders)
  A paper Wyss wrote while a graduate student in 1999: "Women on the Edge of the Transgender Era: Struggling to Throw Off Lesbian Feminism's Legacy," and correspondence written to friends and family during and after her time at Vassar.
  Note: Due to third-party privacy issues, the correspondence in this collection is currently restricted.
Container List
- Series I. Tobias Anderson (VC 1998), 1992-2002
  - Journal No. 1 - "Journal to Austria,", 1992 Aug - 1993 Jun (Folder 1.1)
  - Journal No. 2 - "English Journal" and "College Journal," with letter from Rana Nichols-Kiley, 1993-1994, 1996 (Folder 1.2)
  - Journal No. 3 - "Back to Austria,", 1994-1995, 1999 (Folder 1.3)
  - Journal No. 4 - "Hindu Journal,", circa 1995-1998 (Folder 1.4)
  - Journal No. 5, 1993-1999 (Folder 1.5)
  - Journal No. 6, circa 1999-2000 (Folder 1.6)
  - Journal No. 7, circa 2000 (Folder 1.7)
  - Journal No. 8, circa 2000-2001 (Folder 1.8)
  - Journal No. 9, circa 2001 (Folder 1.9)
  - Journal No. 10, circa 2000-2002 (Folders 1.10-1.11)
  - Journal No. 11, undated (Folder 1.12)
  - Journal No. 12 - "Dream Journal,", undated (Folder 1.13)
- Series II. Carlos Baguer (VC 1996)
  - "No Se Dice Nada, Se Haga Todo": The Not-So-Secret History of My Familial Closet, 1996; [RESTRICTED] (Folder 1.14)
- Series III. Jeffrey Lieber (VC 1997), 1993
  - Untitled paper for English 101, 1993 Dec (Folder 1.15)
- Series IV. Anne MacKay (VC 1949), 1984-2002
  - Wolf Girls at Vassar
    - General files related to the writing and publishing of the book
      - First Edition - Notes, expenses, drafts, and correspondence, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.16)
      - Second Edition - Notes, drafts, and correspondence, 1993 (Folder 1.17)
      - First requests/communications and unused letters, 1991-1999 (Folder 1.18)
      - Permissions, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.19)
      - Promotion, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.20)
      - Related materials and other Vassar stories, 1991-1993 (Folder 1.21)
      - Reviews and letters about the book, 1992-1993 (Folder 1.22)
      - Sources, undated (Folder 1.23)
    - Contributor correspondence and biographical pieces
      - VC 1934 - Muriel Rukeyser, 1991 (Folder 1.24)
      - VC 1940 - Lenore Thompson Kukle, 1991-1993 (Folder 1.25)
      - VC 1949 - Anne Mackay, undated (Folder 1.26)
      - VC 1950s - [Name withheld], undated (Folder 1.29)
      - VC 1950 - Mary Romig, 1990-1994 (Folder 1.27)
      - VC 1952 - Nancy Dean, 1991 (Folder 1.28)
      - VC 1952 - Pat Wilbert, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.30)
      - VC 1955 - Phoebe Shock, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.31)
      - VC 1959 - Cristina Biaggi, 1991-1993 (Folder 1.32)
      - VC 1959 - Gail Ellen Dunlap, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.33)
      - VC 1960 - Betsy Crowell, 1991-1993 (Folder 1.34)
      - VC 1960 - [Name withheld], 1990-1992 (Folder 1.35)
      - VC 1961 - Lucy Cross, 1991 (Folder 1.36)
      - VC 1961 - Charoula Dontopoulos, circa 1991 (Folder 1.37)
      - VC 1962 - Ellen Shee-Bierhorst, 1991-1992 (Folder 1.38)
      - VC 1961 - Beva Eastman, 1990-1991 (Folder 1.39)
      - VC 1964 - [Name withheld], 1990-1991 (Folder 1.40)
      - VC 1967 - Nancy S. Erickson, 1991 (Folder 1.41)
      - VC 1968 - Pat Cain, 1989-1991 (Folder 1.42)
      - VC 1968 - Karin L. Abbey, 1990-1993 (Folder 2.1)
      - VC 1969 - Ellen Anthony, 1991-1994 (Folder 2.2)
      - VC 1970 - Ann Northrop, 1990-1991 (Folder 2.3)
      - VC 1971 - Bonita Ann Palmer, 1990-1992 (Folder 2.4)
      - VC 1971 - [Name withheld], 1990-1991 (Folder 2.5)
      - VC 1972 - Ann E. Menasche, 1991 (Folder 2.6)
      - VC 1973 - Carla Duke, 1990-1992 (Folder 2.7)
      - VC 1974 - Julian de Rothschild-Blau, 1991 (Folder 2.8)
      - VC 1974 - [Name withheld], 1991-1992 (Folder 2.9)
      - VC 1975 - David Pittman, 1991 (Folder 2.10)
      - VC 1975 - Deidre McCalla, 1991 (Folder 2.11)
      - VC 1978 - Name withheld, 1990-1993 (Folder 2.12)
      - VC 1980 - Daniel Aibel, 1991 (Folder 2.13)
      - VC 1980 - George Tirre, 1990-1991 (Folder 2.14)
      - VC 1983 - Lisa Malachowsky, 1990-1991 (Folder 2.15)
      - VC 1983 - Colin D. O'Connell, 1991 (Folder 2.16)
      - VC 1984 - Susan Williams, 1991 (Folder 2.17)
      - VC 1986 - Leslie F. Klein, 1991-1994 (Folder 2.18)
      - VC 1988 - Jill Oppenheim, 1990 (Folder 2.19)
      - VC 1989 - Jana Rich, 1991 (Folder 2.20)
      - VC 1989 - Valarie Walker, 1991 (Folder 2.21)
      - VC 1990 - Karin Cook, 1991 (Folder 2.22)
      - VC 1990 - Kim Glickman, 1991-1993 (Folder 2.23)
  - Other Writings
    - "Breaking the Silence," drafts and responses, 1990 (Folder 2.24)
    - "Just Lucky, I Guess!: Memoirs of a Wolf Girl or Growing up in Sheep's Clothing,", 1995 (Folders 2.25-2.26)
    - Miscellaneous Vassar Writings, 1984-1996 (Folder 3.1)
    - "Recent Poems, Mostly Lesbian,", 1999 (Folder 3.2)
    - "Poems, Mostly Lesbian,", 2000 (Folder 3.3)
    - "Lesbian Poems, 1943-2002,", circa 2002 (Folder 3.4)
    - Vassar speeches, undated; (audiotape) (Folder 3.5)
- Series V. Shannon Wyss (VC 1995), 1991-2000
  - Correspondence, 1991-2000; [RESTRICTED] (Folder 3.6)
  - "Women on the Edge of the Transgender Era: Struggling to Throw Off Lesbian Feminism's Legacy,", 1999 (Folder 3.7)